Hello, everyone, and welcome back to another lesson here at EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎回到EnglishPod的另一节课。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
And my name is Katrin.
我是Katrin。
So, Marco, what are we talking about today?
那么，Marco，我们今天要聊什么？
Today, we are taking a look at a guy who is a little bit too afraid of people in general.
今天，我们要看一个对别人有点过于害怕的家伙。
There's a good word for this in English, someone who's almost too afraid all the time, someone
英语里有个好词来形容这种人，一个几乎总是过度害怕的人，一个
who is overly cautious.
过于谨慎的人。
We call this person paranoid.
我们称这种人为偏执狂。
Okay, so if you are paranoid, you think that everyone wants to hurt you or that everyone
好吧，如果你偏执，你会觉得每个人都想伤害你，或者每个人都
is out to get you.
在算计你。
Wait, did you hear that?
等等，你听到了吗？
No, I didn't.
不，我没听到。
Did you hear that?
你听到了吗？
Someone at the door.
有人在门口。
Marco, can you check that?
Marco，你能去看看吗？
Okay, that's paranoid.
好吧，这就是偏执。
You know, you're always hearing voices and noises and things.
你知道，你总是听到声音和动静什么的。
Yeah, so a paranoid, somebody that is paranoid.
是啊，所以偏执狂，就是那种偏执的人。
All right, so why don't we listen to this dialogue for the first time and see what this
好了，那我们第一次听这段对话，看看这个
person is all paranoid about.
人在为什么事情偏执。
There he is again.
他又来了。
Dan, Dan, dude, you have to come over to my house right now.
Dan，Dan，老兄，你现在就得来我家。
Is everything okay?
一切都还好吗？
Just get over here.
赶紧过来。
Come in, quickly.
快进来。
So since when is your house a bank?
所以你家什么时候变成银行了？
What do you mean?
你什么意思？
I mean, what's up with the four locks and iron bars on your windows?
我是说，你窗户上那四把锁和铁栏杆是怎么回事？
Security Dan, security.
安全措施，Dan，安全措施。
You can never be too safe, you know.
你知道，再怎么小心都不为过。
A lot of sickos out there.
外面有很多变态。
Just the other day, they caught that peeping Tom red handed, had a high power telescope
就在前几天，他们当场抓住了那个偷窥狂，他窗户边放着高倍望远镜
and binoculars by his window.
和双筒望远镜。
What's the matter with you?
你怎么了？
Why are you acting all paranoid?
你为什么表现得这么偏执？
Paranoid?
偏执？
I'm not paranoid.
我不偏执。
I'm cautious.
我是谨慎。
You see, Dan, we have to be on guard at all times.
你看，Dan，我们必须时刻保持警惕。
People just invade your privacy as if they knew you.
人们就像认识你一样侵犯你的隐私。
Telemarketers, solicitors, even your bank, they have way too much information.
电话推销员、上门推销员，甚至你的银行，他们掌握的信息太多了。
I like to keep everything on a need to know basis.
我喜欢一切按需知原则来。
Okay, well, what did you want to see me about?
好吧，那你找我有什么事？
You're being watched.
你被监视了。
Be careful, Dan.
小心点，Dan。
Be careful.
小心点。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So, yeah, I think this guy is a little bit too cautious.
所以，是啊，我觉得这家伙有点过于谨慎了。
I would have to agree with you and I would go so far as to call him paranoid.
我同意你的看法，我甚至会说他是偏执狂。
But there's a lot of great stuff in this dialogue that we can use in a lot of different situations.
但这段对话里有很多好东西，我们可以在很多不同场合使用。
So let's take a look at some of these new words in today's language takeaway.
那我们来看看今天“语言要点”中的一些新词。
Language takeaway.
语言要点。
All right, the first word on language takeaway today is sicko.
好的，今天“语言要点”的第一个词是sicko。
Sicko is also the name of a movie that was a documentary famous in America by Michael
Sicko也是一部电影的名字，是迈克尔·摩尔在美国拍的一部著名纪录片。
Moore actually.
实际上。
But a sicko in this context means someone who is a bit weird in a bad way.
但在这个语境下，sicko指的是一个有点坏心眼、古怪的人。
So if you tell somebody you're sick, but like in that tone, right, you're saying you're
所以如果你对某人说你病了，但用那种语气，对吧，你是在说
sick, you're a sick person.
你病了，你是个有病的人。
You're gross.
你真恶心。
Right.
对。
You're saying you're gross.
你是在说你真恶心。
So people who have inappropriate humor, who make jokes about not so nice things.
所以那些有不恰当幽默感、拿不太好的事情开玩笑的人。
Right.
对。
Yeah, they're sick.
是啊，他们有病。
But in this case, sickos are people who maybe like to hurt other people, people who are
但在这个例子里，sickos指的是可能喜欢伤害别人的人，有点
a little bit crazy, people who are not normal.
疯狂的人，不正常的人。
So it's not a nice way of calling someone crazy, right?
所以这不是一个说某人疯了的友善方式，对吧？
If you say, oh, he's a sicko, it's not really nice.
如果你说，哦，他是个变态，这不太友好。
Not at all.
一点也不。
It's a way of saying that you're almost scared of this person because they're kind of weird
这是一种表达你几乎害怕这个人的方式，因为他们有点古怪
and almost they have problems.
而且几乎有问题。
All right.
好的。
So that's a sicko.
所以这就是sicko。
Moving on to our next word.
接着看下一个词。
We saw that the guy was afraid of telemarketers.
我们看到那个人害怕电话推销员。
Exactly.
没错。
So what are these guys?
那这些人是什么？
Well, we've got two words being put together here, tele and market.
嗯，这里有两个词组合在一起，tele和market。
So tele, like telephone, telephone, over communication.
所以tele，像电话，通过通信。
So they're not in person.
所以他们不是面对面。
They're people who call you up and market things.
他们是打电话给你推销东西的人。
They try to sell you stuff over the phone.
他们试图通过电话卖东西给你。
So this is very common.
这很常见。
You get a phone call on your cell phone and they ask you if you're happy with your long
你手机接到电话，他们问你对你现在的长途
distance calling plan or if you need new TV cable or something like that.
通话计划是否满意，或者你是否需要新的电视电缆之类的。
And they always call during dinner or late at night, which drives me nuts.
而且他们总是在晚餐时间或深夜打电话，这让我抓狂。
So these are telemarketers.
所以这些就是telemarketers。
These are people who call you trying to sell things to you.
这些是打电话给你试图卖东西的人。
And very similar to these is a solicitor.
和这些很相似的是solicitor。
Exactly.
没错。
But the big difference here with solicitors and telemarketers is that solicitors actually
但solicitor和telemarketer的主要区别在于，solicitor实际上
go to your house.
会去你家。
They knock on your door.
他们敲你的门。
So they're also called door to door salesmen or saleswomen.
所以他们也被称为上门推销员。
That's right.
没错。
Door to door salesmen.
上门推销员。
They go from door to door trying to sell things.
他们挨家挨户地试图卖东西。
But in this case, a solicitor is someone who comes to your house to try to get you to do
但在这个例子里，solicitor是来你家试图让你做
something, to buy something.
某事、买东西的人。
All right.
好的。
Very good.
很好。
And moving on to our next word, we have a peeping Tom.
接着看下一个词，我们有peeping Tom。
That's right.
没错。
We heard this a little bit earlier in the dialogue.
我们之前在对话里听到过这个词。
And a peeping Tom is again a negative thing to say about someone.
而peeping Tom又是一个说某人的负面词汇。
A peeping Tom, well, the word peep means to look, but kind of like, yeah, it's a quick
Peeping Tom，嗯，peep这个词意思是看，但有点像，是啊，是快速
look.
看一眼。
A peeping Tom is a person who spies on other people.
Peeping Tom是指偷窥别人的人。
Okay.
好的。
So a synonym of a peeping Tom would be a voyeur.
所以peeping Tom的同义词是voyeur。
A voyeur.
偷窥者。
So someone who, without getting caught, tries to look at other people while they're in their
所以是指那些不被发现、试图看别人在家里的
homes.
情况的人。
And so it's really bad because it's usually inappropriate.
这真的很糟糕，因为这通常是不恰当的。
It's usually people who are watching women get undressed or...
通常是那些看女人脱衣服或……的人。
Right.
对。
So a peeping Tom is just an informal way of saying a voyeur or somebody who is spying on
所以peeping Tom是voyeur或偷窥别人的非正式说法。
people.
对。
So those are the words for today in Language Takeaway.
这些就是今天“语言要点”中的词。
Let's listen to our dialogue again and then we'll be right back.
我们再听一遍对话，然后马上回来。
Dan, Dan, dude, you have to come over to my house right now.
丹，丹，老兄，你现在就得来我家。
Is everything okay?
一切都还好吗？
Just get over here.
赶紧过来。
Come in, quickly.
快进来。
So since when is your house a bank?
所以你家什么时候变成银行了？
What do you mean?
你什么意思？
I mean, what's up with the four locks and iron bars on your windows?
我是说，你窗户上那四把锁和铁栏杆是怎么回事？
Security, Dan!
安全措施，丹！
Security!
安全！
You can never be too safe, you know.
再怎么小心都不为过，你知道的。
A lot of sickos out there.
外面变态多得很。
Just the other day, they caught that peeping Tom red-handed.
就在前几天，他们当场抓住了那个偷窥狂。
Had a high-power telescope and binoculars by his window.
他窗户边放着高倍望远镜和双筒望远镜。
What's the matter with you?
你怎么了？
Why are you acting all paranoid?
你为什么表现得这么疑神疑鬼的？
Paranoid?
疑神疑鬼？
I'm not paranoid!
我才没有疑神疑鬼！
I'm cautious!
我是谨慎！
You see, Dan, we have to be on guard at all times.
你看，丹，我们必须时刻保持警惕。
People just invade your privacy as if they knew you.
人们就像认识你一样侵犯你的隐私。
Telemarketers, solicitors, even your bank.
电话推销员、上门推销员，甚至你的银行。
They have way too much information.
他们掌握的信息太多了。
I like to keep everything on a need-to-know basis.
我喜欢凡事按需告知。
Okay.
好吧。
Well, what did you want to see me about?
嗯，那你找我有什么事？
You're being watched!
你被监视了！
Be careful, Dan.
小心点，丹。
Be careful.
小心点。
Now we're back and we had some interesting phrases in the dialogue.
现在我们回来了，对话中有一些有趣的短语。
The first one being, you can never be too safe.
第一个是“再怎么小心都不为过”。
Fluency Builder.
流利度训练。
Alright, so this is a common mom phrase.
好了，这是一个常见的妈妈式说法。
You often hear mothers say this when they're sending their kids off to school or whatever.
你经常听到妈妈们在送孩子上学之类的时候说这个。
They say, don't talk to strangers and the kid says, well, why not?
她们会说，别跟陌生人说话，然后孩子问，为什么不行？
You can never be too safe.
再怎么小心都不为过。
It's good to err on the side of caution.
宁可谨慎过头也好。
So it's okay to be extra, extra safe or extra cautious, just in case.
所以多一分安全或多一分谨慎是没问题的，以防万一。
Exactly.
没错。
You never know what's going to happen, so it's better to be cautious than not.
你永远不知道会发生什么，所以谨慎总比不谨慎好。
And that's what this person is saying.
这就是这个人想说的。
He's saying, well, security, it's important.
他在说，嗯，安全很重要。
You can never be too safe.
再怎么小心都不为过。
You never know what might happen.
你永远不知道会发生什么。
Is there another way that we can combine it?
有没有另一种说法可以搭配使用？
Like you can never be too careful?
比如“再怎么小心都不为过”？
Exactly.
没错。
Basically, the same thing.
基本上是一样的意思。
Same thing.
一样的意思。
Yeah.
是的。
Alright.
好的。
What's our next phrase?
下一个短语是什么？
We're going to talk about this peeping Tom, this person that they caught.
我们要谈谈这个偷窥狂，他们抓住的那个人。
They caught him red-handed.
他们当场抓住了他。
We caught you red-handed.
我们当场抓住了你。
Or he's been caught red-handed.
或者他被当场抓住了。
So what does that mean?
那是什么意思？
It's a very colorful phrase and I don't just mean that because we're calling him red-handed,
这是一个很生动的短语，我这么说不仅仅是因为我们叫他“红手”，
but to catch red-handed means to catch someone while they're doing something wrong.
而是“当场抓住”的意思是在某人做坏事时抓住他。
So if I see you breaking into someone's house and I say, Marco, stop.
所以如果我看到你闯入别人家，我说，马可，住手。
I'm catching you.
我抓住你了。
Stop now.
马上停下。
I just caught you red-handed.
我刚刚当场抓住了你。
You saw me doing the act.
你看到我在做那件事。
Exactly.
没错。
And another way of saying this is you caught him with his hand in the cookie jar.
另一种说法是“你抓到他手伸进饼干罐里了”。
Okay.
好的。
And this is another great phrase.
这也是一个很棒的短语。
You can imagine a child who sees the cookies in a very special jar on the counter in the
你可以想象一个孩子看到厨房台子上一个特别的罐子里的饼干，
kitchen and mom says, don't eat the cookies.
妈妈说，别吃饼干。
Well, the child goes into the kitchen and sees the cookies and opens the jar and puts
然后孩子走进厨房，看到饼干，打开罐子，
his hand in the jar and then mom comes and says, caught you.
把手伸进去，这时妈妈过来说，抓住你了。
That's a boy with his hand or a child with their hand in the cookie jar.
那就是一个手伸进饼干罐里的孩子。
So it's the same thing.
所以是一样的意思。
I can say, I caught you with your hand in the cookie jar.
我可以说，我抓到你手伸进饼干罐里了。
Or you were caught red-handed.
或者你被当场抓住了。
All right.
好的。
And our last phrase for today is you are on a need to know basis.
今天最后一个短语是“你按需告知”。
All right.
好的。
This is a great one.
这个很棒。
This is often said in spy movies, I think.
我觉得这经常在间谍电影里出现。
So we say you're on a need to know basis.
所以我们说“你按需告知”。
That means that if you really need to know something, then I will tell you.
意思是如果你真的需要知道某件事，那我就会告诉你。
But if not, I won't.
但如果不需要，我就不说。
So you only have the information that is necessary.
所以你只拥有必要的信息。
No more or less.
不多不少。
You're on a need to know basis.
你按需告知。
Right.
对。
So I say, tell me, Marco, tell me what happened.
所以我说，告诉我，马可，告诉我发生了什么。
I want to know.
我想知道。
Right.
对。
And I can say, no, no, you're on a need to know basis and you don't need to know this.
然后我可以说，不，不，你按需告知，你不需要知道这个。
All right.
好的。
So a need to know basis, as you say, very popular among spy movies and government movies
所以按需告知，就像你说的，在间谍电影和政府电影里很常见，
and stuff like that.
还有类似的东西。
Conspiracy movies.
阴谋论电影。
Yeah.
是的。
All right.
好的。
So let's listen to this dialogue for the very last time and we'll be right back.
那么让我们最后再听一遍这段对话，我们马上回来。
Dan, Dan, dude, you have to come over to my house right now.
丹，丹，老兄，你现在就得来我家。
Is everything okay?
一切都还好吗？
Just get over here.
赶紧过来。
Come in quickly.
快进来。
So since when is your house a bank?
所以你家什么时候变成银行了？
What do you mean?
你什么意思？
I mean, what's up with the four locks and iron bars on your windows?
我是说，你窗户上那四把锁和铁栏杆是怎么回事？
Security, Dan security.
安全措施，丹，安全。
You can never be too safe.
再怎么小心都不为过。
You know, a lot of sickos out there.
你知道，外面变态多得很。
Just the other day, they caught that heaping Tom red handed, had a high power telescope
就在前几天，他们当场抓住了那个偷窥狂，他窗户边放着高倍望远镜
and binoculars by his window.
和双筒望远镜。
What's the matter with you?
你怎么了？
Why are you acting all paranoid?
你为什么表现得这么疑神疑鬼的？
Paranoid?
疑神疑鬼？
I'm not paranoid.
我才没有疑神疑鬼。
I'm cautious.
我是谨慎。
You see, Dan, we have to be on guard at all times.
你看，丹，我们必须时刻保持警惕。
People just invade your privacy as if they knew you.
人们就像认识你一样侵犯你的隐私。
Telemarketers, solicitors, even your bank.
电话推销员、上门推销员，甚至你的银行。
They have way too much information.
他们掌握的信息太多了。
I like to keep everything on a need to know basis.
我喜欢凡事按需告知。
Okay.
好的。
Well, what did you want to see me about?
嗯，你想见我有什么事？
You're being watched.
你被监视了。
Be careful, Dan.
小心点，丹。
Be careful.
小心点。
All right.
好吧。
So the guy's a little bit paranoid.
所以这家伙有点偏执。
There's another word for this as well.
还有一个词也可以形容这个。
Similar, right?
类似，对吧？
It's schizo.
是“精神分裂”。
Schizophrenia is a disease and a lot of people have it and it's not too uncommon, but a popular
精神分裂症是一种疾病，很多人都有，并不罕见，但一个流行的
slang word to say someone's crazy is schizo.
俚语说某人疯了就是“精神分裂”。
So if you guys remember this movie, A Beautiful Mind, it's all about this famous mathematician.
所以如果你们记得这部电影《美丽心灵》，它讲的是这位著名的数学家。
He's named John Nash.
他叫约翰·纳什。
And well, he was a genius.
嗯，他是个天才。
He came up with game theory and a lot of subsequent usage of this for economy, for many things.
他提出了博弈论，后来被广泛应用于经济学和许多领域。
But it was proven that he was a schizophrenic, right?
但事实证明他患有精神分裂症，对吧？
A paranoid schizophrenic.
一种偏执型精神分裂症。
So not only did he kind of have experienced reality in different ways, but he's also paranoid.
所以他不仅以不同方式体验现实，而且还偏执。
So he was afraid that the government was trying to kill him.
所以他害怕政府要杀他。
And so he was, he was irrationally afraid of everything going on around him.
所以他对他周围发生的一切都毫无理性地害怕。
And it made him very unsafe because he could hurt himself or hurt other people.
这让他非常不安全，因为他可能伤害自己或伤害别人。
And the interesting thing about this is that there is no actual cure for it.
有趣的是，这实际上没有治愈方法。
You just learn to cope and live with it.
你只能学会应对并与之共存。
So you never really get cured.
所以你永远不会真正痊愈。
You just kind of live with it.
你只是学着与之共存。
Learn how to understand what's real and what's not.
学会理解什么是真实的，什么不是。
So it's interesting.
所以这很有趣。
It's a great movie also, by the way, if you've never seen it or you get a chance to watch
顺便说一句，这也是一部很棒的电影，如果你没看过或有机会看
it.
的话。
And that's all the time we have for today.
这就是我们今天的所有时间。
So if you have any questions, doubts or comments, please come to our website, EnglishPod.com
所以如果你有任何问题、疑问或评论，请访问我们的网站 EnglishPod.com
and we're there to answer them.
我们会在那里回答。
Yeah, we hope to see you there.
是的，我们希望在那里见到你。
And until next time, English Poddies.
下次再见，英语播客的朋友们。
All right.
好的。
Bye.
再见。